Finding Aid for Dick Posthumus papers, 1972-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dick Posthumus papers 1972-2002 1982-2002
Posthumus, Dick, 1950-
0729 Aa 2
The Dick Posthumus papers (1972-2002) consist of materials related to his political career as state senator, Senate Majority Leader, and Lieutenant Governor and his campaign for governor. The collection includes correspondence, campaign literature, media advisories, newspaper clippings, speeches, radio and television appearances and photographs.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dick Posthumus 9838 and came to the library in 2007.
The collection is open to research.
Dick Posthumus was born in 1950 and grew up on a dairy farm outside of Grand Rapids. He graduated from Caledonia High School in 1968 and continued his education at Michigan State University, where he majored in agricultural economics and public affairs management. While at Michigan State, he was chair of the College Republicans and served as chair of the Michigan State University Republican Party. After graduating from Michigan State University, Posthumus served in several key staff positions in the House of Representatives and management positions with the Michigan Beef Industry Commission and the Farmers' and Manufacturers' Beet Sugar Association, as well as established himself as a farmer. In 1971, Posthumus served as John Engler's campaign manager in Engler's successful campaign for state representative. This began a political partnership that lasted over 30 years.
In 1982, Posthumus was elected to the State Senate, representing the 31st Senatorial District, which includes Kent County. In 1990, he became the Senate Majority Leader and is noted for the longest leadership in Michigan history. Posthumus joined Governor Engler on the ticket as Lieutenant Governor in 1998 and went on to serve in that post for four years. He was the Republican nominee for governor in 2002, having defeated State Senator Joe Schwarz in the Republican primary, but lost to Democrat Jennifer Granholm in the general election by approximately 4%.
Posthumus is most known for his 1994 initiative Proposal A, which cut state property taxes and reformulated the way Michigan funded public schools, sponsoring a bill that created charter schools in Michigan, and acting as chief sponsor of bills that created Renaissance Zones, which offered opportunities and revitalization for business owners and cities. As Lieutenant Governor, Posthumus chaired the Michigan Domestic Violence Homicide Prevention Task Force that provided recommendations to eliminate homicides resulting from domestic violence.
Dick Posthumus resides on a family farm in Alto, Michigan with his wife Pam. They have four children and three grandchildren. In 2005 he joined Compatico, a Grand Rapids office furniture manufacturing firm, and became CEO in 2006.
The Dick Posthumus papers (1972-2002) consist of materials related to his political career as state senator, Senate Majority Leader, and Lieutenant Governor and his campaign for governor. The collection includes correspondence, campaign literature, media advisories, newspaper clippings, speeches, radio and television appearances and photographs. The papers are organized into eight series: materials related to his political career as a state senator, Senate Majority Leader, and Lieutenant Governor and his campaign for governor: Campaigns, Correspondence, Media Advisories, News clips, Speeches, Topical Files, Other Media, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Posthumus, Dick, 1950-; Lieutenant governors--Michigan.; Michigan. Lieutenant Governor.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Republican Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1982.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Posthumus, Dick, 1950-; Political elections--Michigan.; Michigan. Lieutenant Governor.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Republican Party (Mich.); Engler, John, 1948-; Political conventions--Michigan.; Politics & government--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--2002.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Compact discs.; DVDs.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Campaigns
  The Campaigns series (0.5 linear feet) focuses largely on Posthumus's 1982 campaign for state senate and includes correspondence and endorsements, campaign literature, election results, strategy and finance records, and press releases. Also included is published campaign literature for his campaigns in 1998 and 2002.
  - 1982
    - Correspondence and Endorsements, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Literature, Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1)
    - Official Election Results (Box 1)
    - Strategy and Finance (Box 1)
    - Updates and Press Releases (Box 1)
  - Other campaigns
    - Published campaign materials (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1983-2002
  Correspondence (0.5 linear feet) is arranged chronologically by year and spans Posthumus's political career from 1983 to 2002.
  - 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (candidate correspondence) (Box 1)
  - 1998 (congratulatory notes), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1994 (Box 1)
  - 1999-2002 (Box 1)
- Media Advisories 1999-2002
  Media Advisories (1.0 linear feet) are arranged chronologically and contain releases to local and state presses during his time as Lieutenant Governor, 1999-2002. The Other Media series includes a CD with more media advisories.
  - 1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 2000 (Box 2)
  - 2001, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - 2002, 4 folders (Box 2)
- News clips 1982-2002
  News clips (2.5 linear feet) are arranged into two groups, bound and unbound. The clips from 1994-1998 have an index. The news clips are related to his political career and campaigns. The staff file CD in the Other Media series contains more news clippings.
  - Bound
    - 1982-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994 (Box 3)
    - 1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996 (Box 3)
    - January-July 1997 (Box 3)
    - August 1997-June 5, 1998 (Box 3)
    - January-July 1998 (Box 3)
    - August-December 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 4)
    - 2000 (Box 4)
    - January-July 2001 (Box 4)
    - August-December 2001 (Box 4)
    - January-March 2002 (Box 4)
    - April-June 2002 (Box 4)
    - July-September 2002, 2 volumes (Box 4)
    - October-November 2002 (Box 4)
    - Index 1994-1998 (Box 4)
  - Unbound
    - 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    - 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1994-2002 (Box 5)
- Speeches 1989-2001
  Speeches (0.5 linear feet) are arranged chronologically by year from 1989-2001 and span his career as Senate Majority Leader and half of his time as Lieutenant Governor. The staff file CD includes additional speeches.
  - 1989-1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1997, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1998 (Box 5)
  - 2001 (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (0.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and include biographical materials, brochures and programs, Inaugural Day speeches and events, his event schedule, reports from his time as Senate Majority Leader and a binder from the 1972 GOP Convention.
  - Biographies and resumes (Box 6)
  - Brochures and programs (Box 6)
  - Lieutenant Governor
    - Domestic Violence Homicide Prevention Task Force Report April 2001 (Box 6)
    - Inaugural address and events (Box 6)
    - Inauguration pamphlet (Box 6)
    - Tracking (Box 6)
  - Senate
    - 1985 Visit Summaries (Box 6)
    - Senate Wrap-Ups 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Senate Wrap-Ups 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - 1998 Senate Audit Report (Box 6)
  - 1972 GOP Convention (Box 6)
- Other Media
  Other Media (0.5 linear feet) are arranged by media format (3.5" floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, and VHS). This series includes photo CDs, audio clips, video compilations of Posthumus during his governor campaign, videos of his opponent, Jennifer Granholm, and a CD of staff files that include press releases, photos and speeches.
  - 3.5" Floppy
    - 2002 Picture Disks, 4 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 6)
  - CD
    - Domestic Violence Prevention audio clips, 2 optical disks CDs (Box 6)
  - CD-ROM
    - Staff Files, 1 optical disks CD-Rs
      - Kristyn Files, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 6)
      - Matt Press Releases, Photos and Speeches, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 6)
  - DVD
    - 2002 Compilation, 2 optical disks DVDs (Box 6)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - Granholm Compilation #1 (with notes in separate folder), 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 6)
    - Granholm: "Tweak to Capture Resources", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 6)
    - "Fox and Friends: Lt. Governor" June 1, 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 6)
    - "Posthumus 2002 Compilation", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 6)
    - "Posthumus for Governor", 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 6)
- Photographs
  Photographs (1.0 linear feet) are arranged in part by subject and otherwise chronologically by decade. The chronologically arranged photographs are miscellaneous photographs with unidentifiable dates and people but typically feature interactions with constituents and politicians. Photographs arranged by subject include those autographed and with prominent politicians, family, on the campaign trails, headshots of Posthumus, and those taken with Governor John Engler. The researcher should note that the staff file CD and the floppy discs in the Other Media series contains additional digital photographs.
  - 1970s (Box 7)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 7)
  - 1990-1999, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 2000-2002 (Box 7)
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Autographed and Prominent People: include Mr. And Mrs. George H. W. Bush, Mr. and Mrs. George W. Bush, Bill Clinton, Mr. and Mrs. Dan Quayle, Arnold Schwarzenegger, Dick Cheney, and Jeff Daniels (Box 7)
  - Family (Box 7)
  - Farm Fest 1994 (Box 7)
  - Golf Outings 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - Governor and Lieutenant Governor Campaigns (Box 7)
  - Habitat for Humanity 1994, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Headshots, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Michigan Department of Transportation 1999, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Republican Conventions (Box 7)
  - Trips to Asia (Box 7)
  - With Children (Box 7)
  - With John Engler (Box 7)